なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜宇宙飛行士候補生
アスキャンの➡
We astronaut candidates, or ASCANs,
合同訓練のため
アメリカ･ヒューストンに➡
have arrived in Houston, USA, for joint basic training.
やってきた私達＞
ひびと
《こいつが日々人の兄貴か》
This is Hibito's older brother?
ふぬ
(ビンス)《腑抜けた顔をしてる｡
当然 軍隊経験もなし｡➡
He looks rather dim.
Naturally, he has no military experience.
弟に後れをとってる上に
この締りのない腑抜け顔｡➡
He's a step behind his little brother,
and he looks like a fool.
救いようのないノロマだと
すぐ分かる》
It's clear that he's a lost cause.
＜私は占いが
ことごとく当たるという➡
I asked Amanti, a candidate from India who's supposedly
インドから来た候補生
アマンティに➡
an accurate fortune teller, to see what my future had in store...
今後の展望的なことを
見てもらったのだが…＞
Sure...
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)そうね…｡
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)そ…そうね｡なんか
すごく いい感じよ｡
R-Right...
It will go very well...
え…ホント ホントに？
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)ホント ホント｡
Huh? Really?
R-Really...
《ちょっと待て…明らかに…➡
Hold on...
Amanti looked very disturbed for a moment there.
ふおん
不穏な表情したよな アマンティ》
ふんっ｡
アクセルを いつもより
３センチ踏み込むだけです｡
I depress the pedal an extra three centimeters.
Three centimeters is all I need
その たった３センチだけで…｡
よか
１日に１時間の余暇が生じます｡
to gain an extra hour per day.
うわさ
(ｼｪｲﾝ)ボールドさんて 噂通り
時間に厳しい方ですね｡
Rumor has it that you're pretty uptight about time.
でも確かに １時間は
でかいかもな ベン｡
But an hour definitely helps, Ben.
(ベン)そりゃ そうだ｡
Definitely.
１日に１時間ってことは
１年で見ると 365時間でぇ➡
Over a year, an hour per day would total three hundred, sixty-five hours.
１５日分も得することになるな｡➡
That's fifteen whole days...
宇宙飛行士の１５日は でかい｡
For an astronaut, fifteen days is huge.
(ｼｪｲﾝ)ボールドさん
窓 開けてみてい～っすか？
Bold...
Could I open the window?
え～っと これって…｡
Uh, is this the switch?
あっ｡おおっ！
す…っげ！
息できねぇな こりゃ！➡
Amazing...
I can hardly breathe.
だが そこがまたいい！
But that's the best part!
《やはり 元軍人である人間は
図太さが違う｡➡
As expected, the former soldiers display stronger nerve.
ベン･ハートは このスピードでも
落ち着いていられる｡➡
Ben Hart is perfectly calm, despite our high velocity.
シェイン･マグワンは
このスピードを➡
Shane Magowan can enjoy the high speed.
楽しむことができる》
《この２人は軍隊経験を経て➡
Through their military training,
they've learned to master their fear.
恐怖に打ち勝つものを
すでに得ている｡話が早い｡➡
That makes my job easier.
それに対して 学生上がりは
決まって そんな顔だ》
But this is how kids straight out of school react.
スピードを上げますよ｡
I'm going to accelerate.
Space Brothers
I can no longer remember
what I tried to forget
When I peeked through the telescope
I realized that our world is tiny
It was a picture of infinity
It's not a one-time thing
We'll walk together
Once we've passed the clouds,
we will hold the world between our fingers
and keep what we lost in mind
#48 Always Have a Pedometer in Your Heart
あ～あ｡
《あ～｡絶対 近いうちに
何かあるんだ…俺の身に…》
Something is about to happen to me very soon.
あっ！この人
大変なことになっちゃう！➡
Oh...
A terrible thing is going to happen to him.
それ言う？
いやいや言えないでしょ～｡
Should I tell him?
No, I couldn't tell him...
《…って顔だったもん アレ》
It was so obvious.
《間違いなく 何か
フキツなモノが見えてるよ…》
She must have seen something ominous.
《いや…しかし…➡
But wait...
にった
新田に弟がいるってのは
ハズれてたし》
She was wrong about Nitta having a younger brother.
So Amanti isn't always right.
かんぺき
《アマンティとて完璧ではない》
Mu!
(ケンジ)ムッ君！
訓練の説明会 始まるよ｡
は～い｡
The training orientation's about to start!
Okay.
Since you have been selected as astronaut candidates, ASCANs,
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)君達が宇宙飛行士候補生
アスキャンとして➡
選ばれた者ならば 私達の話を
一発で理解して下さい｡➡
you should be able to comprehend this explanation the first time through.
私は一度 説明した内容を
何度も訊かれることが嫌いです｡➡
I hate it when people keep asking about topics I've already covered.
It's a waste of time.
時間のムダだからです｡➡
First, you'll need to remember my name.
まずは 私の名前を覚えて下さい｡
ビンセント･ボールド｡
君達の訓練教官を務めます｡
Vincent Bold.
I'll be one of your instructors.
(ラリー)同じく訓練教官を
やらせてもらう➡
I am your other instructor, Larry Bison.
ラリー･バイソンだ｡ヨロシク！
It's a pleasure.
(北村)わあ～何かキビシそ～｡
They look tough...
For some reason, Bold looks familiar.
(せりか)あのボールドさんて
どっかて見たような…｡
かんげい
歓迎パーティーにいたよ あの人｡
え？そうでしたっけ？
He was at the welcome party.
Oh? Really?
店の隅っこに１人座って
ウイスキー飲みながら➡
He was sitting in the corner by himself,
drinking whiskey and eating oysters.
蒸しガキ食べてたよ｡
ピクリともしない無表情で｡
Utterly stone-faced.
へえ～｡
《よく覚えてるなぁ～》
How did he remember all that?
Now, then.
さて これから始まるアスキャンの
合同基礎訓練は２年間に渡ります｡
The upcoming joint ASCAN training will last for two years.
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)そのメニューは ＮＡＳＡ
７０年の経験を基に➡
Developed with the benefit of seventy years of NASA experience,
構成された とても内容の濃い
プログラムになっています｡➡
the training program is quite efficient.
However,
ですが 私からすれば
はっきり言って まだムダが多い｡
I believe there's still some fat that needs trimming!
《ムダなんて あったか～？
詰め詰めだぞ》
I can't remember a thing... They're packing a lot in.
君達は私のやり方に
従ってもらい➡
You will follow my orders...
本来２年間かかる基礎訓練を➡
And you will complete this two-year training program in a year and a half.
１年半以内に
終わらせてもらいます｡
Oh!
《おお！なんか
いいんじゃね～か この人》
I like this guy!
He oozes motivation.
《ものすごい
やる気を感じるぞ！》
《ちょっとでも早く 日々人に
追いつけるんだ｡ありがたいぜ》
This means I can catch up to Hibito even sooner.
Exactly what I wanted.
《あの時 私が感じたことが
外れてればいいけど…》
I hope my premonition was mistaken.
(ﾗﾘｰ)１年半以内って…ハンッ➡
A year and a half?
あんなこと言っちゃっていいの？
ビンス｡
You're sure that's what you wanted to say?
熱っ！あ～また やっちまった｡
Hot! Did it again...
猫舌ですか？
Too hot for you?
昔より覚えること倍増してんのに
１年半以内って…｡
These days, there's twice as much material to learn,
and you want it done in a year and a half?
自信はあります｡
(ﾗﾘｰ)自信なんてのはな➡
I'm confident that it is possible.
Confidence is a temporary condition that lasts until you actually understand a situation.
おのれ
己の現状に気がつくまでの
一時的な気分だぜ｡ハンッ｡
Does that imply that you're confident of nothing?
では君には 自信のあることは
ひとつもないんですか？
いや あるにはある｡
No, I have confidence in some things.
たとえば 俺は一生 この➡
For example...
I'm confident that I'll never quit drinking kiddy orange juice!
お子様オレンヂをやめられねえ！
という自信がある｡
ハンッ あったな 自信｡
あっ そうだ｡
There you go.
Oh, that's right...
見てくれ ビンス｡
１０日後開始のＡ訓練にさ➡
Look at this, Vince.
I'm thinking about using this in ten days, for stage A.
これをやらせようかと
思ってんだよ｡
(ﾗﾘｰ)おんもしろそうだろ？
俺も やりたいくらいだもん｡
Looks fun, right?
I'd love to give it a go...
きみ
なま
ラリー君｡君は｢生ぬるい｣って
よく言われませんか｡
Larry, do people tend to accuse you of being lukewarm?
俺はね コーヒーでもシャワーでも
お子様オレンヂでも➡
Whether it's coffee, showers, or orange juice,
ちょっと ぬるいくらいが
好きなんだよ｡
lukewarm is the way I like it.
わかりました｡
少し先に やる予定でしたが➡
I understand.
This would be earlier than I'd planned,
私の方で用意していた
サバイバル訓練を➡
but we could put them through my survival training before you begin your program.
この前に組み込みましょう｡
場所も同じだし➡
Both sessions take place at the same location, so we'd save travel time.
大幅な時間の短縮になります｡
でも いきなりサバイバるのは
きび
ちょいと厳しいんじゃね～の？
But it's a bit rough, hitting them with survival training, right out of the gate.
Sooner or later, they'll have to pass it.
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)どの道 やることです｡
きみ
ビンス君 君は｢厳しいね｣って
よく言われ…｡
Vince, do people tend to accuse you of being rigid?
Yes.
言われます｡｢せっかち｣ともね｡
They also call me impatient.
(ﾗﾘｰ)で サバイバルを
どう組み込むんだよ？
So, how will we fit survival training into the program?
It's very simple.
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)簡単です｡訓練の出発点を
さばく
砂漠から始めるだけです｡
Their training will begin in the desert.
(ﾗﾘｰ)砂漠!?
The desert?
Amarillo
何てこった…｡
I don't believe this.
１チーム６人制 全５チームに
分かれてもらう｡➡
Divide yourselves into five teams of six.
道具は用意してある｡➡
We have prepared all necessary equipment.
あとは ただ
ひたすら歩いてもらう｡
Once you're ready, begin walking.
それだけだ｡
That will be all.
≪はあ…はあ…≫
はあ…あぢぃ…｡
So hot...
《気温４０度》
Forty degrees.
ゆかげん
《これが風呂なら いい湯加減》
The perfect temperature for a bath.
はあ…はあ…はあ…｡
《背負ってる荷物
１人平均１２キロ》
Each person carries twelve kilograms of equipment...
《私の心の万歩計では とうに
６千歩は超えた頃だが…》
The pedometer in my heart says that we've taken over six thousand steps.
《全っ然 景色に変化なし》
But the scenery hasn't changed at all.
ふふっ…昨日までは
座学の日々だったのに➡
We spent the past month in a classroom, and now, we're thrown into the middle of a desert...
いきなり砂漠でサバイバル生活が
始まるなんてな…｡
でも 南波さん｡
Still, Nanba...
こんなアーミー服着て 本格的に
砂漠でキャンプするなんて➡
Most people are never given the chance to wear military uniforms and camp in the desert.
めったに できない
経験じゃないですか｡うん｡
私 結構 楽しいですよ｡
いやっ むしろ幸せだ！
I'm having a lot of fun...
Yep, I'm thrilled!
確かにね！
いいこと言うな～せりかさんは｡
That's true!
You really know to see the bright side, Serika!
《美人の上に なんて前向きな
人なんだ！でもね せりかさん➡
She's beautiful and optimistic, too.
However, Serika...
そんな事を言っていられるのは
今のうちだけだよ｡➡
You'll change your mind soon enough.
長い旅は まだ始まったばかり》
Our long journey has only just begun.
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)君達３０名には ６日間で
７０キロ先の目的地➡
The thirty of you
will spend the next six days walking the seventy kilometers to Amarillo.
アマリロまで歩いてもらう｡
チームは私が勝手に決めた｡
６人組で Ａ班からＥ班の➡
I've arbitrarily assigned you to teams.
There are five teams, A through E.
５チームだ｡少人数の国の者が
人数の多い国に➡
I've grouped the candidates from countries with the most members, then filled in as necessary.
分散して加わる形にした｡毎日
リーダーを変えて 全員に➡
Every day, you will switch leaders, giving everyone experience with leading and following.
リーダーと それに続く
フォロワーを経験してもらう｡➡
リーダーの仕事は タイムテーブル
道順 歩行距離 食事など➡
The leader's job is to decide such matters as daily schedule, travel direction and distance, meals, etc.
その日一日の すべての行動を
決定してもらう｡
以上だ｡何か質問のある者は
いるか？いないな｡
That is all.
Any questions?
Of course not.
すべての班に 指導員として
２人ずつ 先輩宇宙飛行士が➡
Every team will be accompanied by two veteran astronauts who will serve as advisors.
同行することになっている｡
各チームの地図に➡
Each team will receive a map that indicates the rendezvous point where they will find their advisors.
担当する指導員との合流場所が
記してあるはずだ｡➡
まずは チーム内で 今日一日の
リーダーを決め➡
Your first task is to determine your leader for the day,
指導員に会うことから
始めてくれ｡
and then to meet up with your advisors.
何か質問のある者は
いるか？いないな｡
Any questions?
Of course not.
質問は あんだけどさ
すき
隙がねえんだよな｡
I did have questions,
but no chance to ask them.
あれだ！指導員の車まで
あと少しだよ｡がんばろう！
That's it.
The advisors' vehicle is close.
Hang in there!
ＯＫ！ナイスリーダー！
Okay!
Nice leadership!
あっ！わ～出た！
Right there!
あ～何ですか？
サソリ‼
What is it?
A scorpion!
わっ 危ない せりかさん！ほら
すっげえ威嚇してるよ 俺に！
Be careful, Serika!
Look, it's trying to intimidate me...
(新田)サソリごときで騒ぎすぎだ｡
ただの虫だろ｡
Why are you so afraid of a scorpion?
It's only a bug.
大丈夫ですよ ムッタさん｡
Don't worry, Mutta.
Huh?
あなたは この訓練中 サソリには
刺されません｡安心して｡
You won't be stung by a scorpion during training.
You can relax.
Really?
ほんとに？
Yes.
I see...
そっかあ｡アマンティが言うなら
問題ない｡
If you say so, it must be true.
《サソリ｢には｣刺されません…》
I won't be stung by a scorpion.
But I'll be stung by something else...
《でも何かには 刺されるんだ…》
さあ 行きましょう！
Come, let's get moving.
《いや 考えすぎだ！
考えすぎ…考えすぎ》
No, I'm being too paranoid.
Stop worrying about it so much.
You're late!
遅いっ！他の班なんて とっくに
合流して 昼メシ食ってるって➡
The other teams have already assembled and begun eating lunch.
話だぜ｡お前ら 最下位だ 最下位｡
You're the last to arrive.
まったく 何時間待たせんだよって
話だぜ｡ウチの５つ年下の➡
Honestly, how many hours did you want me to wait?
You're as bad as my wife, who's five years younger...
カミさんかよ お前らは！本気で
帰ろうかと思ったぞ このヤロー｡
I seriously considered leaving.
言っとくけど 俺も宇宙飛行士だ｡
訓練と訓練の多忙状態の中を…｡➡
Just so you know, I'm an astronaut.
I'm busy with my own training, but I guess it's all right.
って まあいいや｡
いや 良くないけど！
No, it isn't all right!
俺は お前らＥ班の
指導員を任されてる➡
I'm Mike Davis, a Team E advisor.
マイク･デイビスだ｡３４歳！
カニ座だがカニは食えねえ！
Thirty-four years old! A Cancer who doesn't eat crab!
おい！お前も 出て来い｡
このヤロー！➡
Hey! Get out here, man.
でもスシは好きだ｡うちのカミさん
が 料理教室で習ってきた｡
But I am a sushi fan.
My wife took a class to learn to prepare it.
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)Ｅ班の指導員２人目
ローリー･クオモだ｡➡
I'm Team E's second advisor, Lowry Cuomo!
I'm here to monitor you.
お前らを監視する｡
Hey, Lowry... It's been a while.
ローリーじゃねえか
久しぶり！
え ２人は知り合いなの？
Huh? You're acquaintances?
知り合いだぁ!?お前らのことなど
たとえ 知っていたとしても…｡
Acquaintances?
If one of you were an acquaintance of mine, you wouldn't be!
知らん！
Huh?
ちょっと！なに言ってんの
ローリー｡
Wait, what are you saying, Lowry?
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)誰だ お前？
まず 名を名乗れ！
Who are you? Identify yourself!
That's enough, Lowry. Back off a little...
もういいぜ ローリー｡
てめえは 引っ込んでな｡
なんなんだよ…｡
What was that about?
Maybe he forgot you, Nanba.
忘れられたんじゃねえの？
南波｡
よくあつてき
《ごめんよ ムッタ｡抑圧的な
口調で 厳しくやり通せって➡
Sorry, Mutta...
Vince ordered us to boss everyone around with an intimidating manner.
ビンスさんの命令なんだよ｡➡
Actually, I'm wearing a T-shirt I really wanted to show you!
本当は 君に見せたいＴシャツを
中に着てるんだよ！》
(ﾏｲｸ)さあて お前ら 遅れた罰だ｡
腕立て伏せ３３回で➡
Okay, chumps...
Punishment for tardiness.
I'll go easy on you and only ask for thirty-three push-ups.
許しといてやる｡俺は ３が
今月のﾗｯｷｰﾅﾝﾊﾞｰなんでな！
Three is my lucky number this month.
腕立て…｡
オッケー！やろう！
Push-ups...
Okay, let's go!
(一同)１…２…３…４…｡
One...
Two...
Three...
Four.
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)はい こちら本部｡
Yes, this is HQ.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ﾏｲｸ)こちら Ｅ班の指導員
マイク･デイビスっす｡➡
This is Team E advisor Mike Davis.
１３時２４分 メンバー６人が
合流ポイントに到着しました｡➡
At 13:24, all six members arrived.
これより 昼食をとらせます｡
We will now have lunch.
Ｅ班最初のリーダーは 誰ですか？
Who is Team E's first leader?
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ﾏｲｸ)リーダーはマカベ･ケンジ
っす｡俺が思うに彼は…｡
Their leader is Makabe Kenji.
He appears to be...
Roger that.
わかりました｡昼食後 予定の
Ｂ訓練へ移行して下さい｡
After lunch, proceed with session B.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ﾏｲｸ)は はいっ！了解っす！
Y-Yes, sir! Roger that!
まあ Ｅ班が一番遅くなるってのは
目に見えてたけどな ハッ…｡
Well, it was obvious that Team E would be the slowest.
他の班には 女は１人ずつだが
Ｅ班だけ３人も…｡
(ビンス)ラリー君｡
The other teams each have one woman,
but Team E has three...
Larry...
男女が持つ能力の差をなくす事も
この訓練の目的の一つです｡➡
One of the objectives of this training is precisely
to eliminate any differences in performance according to gender.
女の人数を ハンデとするのは
タブｰだ｡ただ Ｅ班のメンバｰが➡
Thinking of more women on a team as a handicap is taboo.
And if Team E falls into that trap, they'll be finished.
そう思ってしまったら
もう終わりです｡
You've only been given enough food for lunch.
お前らが最初に受け取った
食料は この昼メシ分だけだ｡➡
今後の食料は 道中で
探してもらうことになるからな｡
From here on, you'll need to forage for your own food supplies...
Thank you for the food!
いただきま～す！
Mike?
マイクさん さっき 僕らＥ班が
最下位だって言ってましたけど➡
You mentioned that we were last to arrive.
この訓練に 順位とか
あるんですか？
Are we being ranked?
ああ あるぜ｡
いちいち あるぜ｡
Yeah, you are.
You bet you are.
(ﾏｲｸ)どの班が 効率良く
スムーズに作業を進めて➡
We're evaluating each team's efficiency and the smoothness of their progress.
どれだけ歩いたかってのを
毎日 本部に連絡する｡➡
Each day, we'll report the distance you traveled to HQ.
単純に 早く距離を稼いだ班が
上位にランク付けされる｡➡
Teams that travel faster are ranked higher.
順位を付けて どうするつもりなの
かは 俺らも知らねえけどな｡➡
Although we weren't told how the ranking will be used...
まあ とりあえず
３位くらいを目指そうぜ｡
Well, see if you can finish third.
なぜなら 今月の俺は
３が いいんだ｡
Because
three is my number this month.
Right...
《順位か…》
Ranking...
(新田)ああ こっちは
今日 始まったばかりだ｡
Yeah, we just began today.
Yeah.
ああ…｡まだか｡わかった｡
Not yet?
Understood.
何だよ 新田
また電話かよ｡
What's going on, Nitta? Another call?
まあな｡電話をかけてくる女が
たくさんいて困る｡
Yeah, I guess.
I always get all these women calling.
《チッ！いいな コノヤロ》
Bah... Lucky bastard.
Are you picking up the pace some, Kenji?
何か ちょっと ペース
速くなってねえか？ケンジ｡➡
初日だぞ 今日｡
It's our first day...
悪い ムッ君｡前半
のんびりし過ぎたみたいだ｡
Sorry, Mu.
Apparently, we walked too slowly this morning.
あと２キロ がんばろう！➡
Let's try for another two kilometers.
この ２キロ先の地帯に
食料が隠してあって➡
Two kilometers up ahead, there's a food cache.
それを見つけて 確保しなきゃ
ならないんだ｡今晩から明日の➡
We need to reach that food.
It should get us through dinner and breakfast.
昼までの食料だ｡日が暮れる前に
見つけないと 大変な事になる｡
If we can't find the food before sunset, we'll be in trouble.
なるほど｡じゃあ急ごう！
Got it.
Then, we should hurry.
I must keep up the pace...
《しっかり ついて行かないと…
足手まといと思われたくない！》
I don't want to hold the team back!
《よし！この先に食料が…》
Yes! There's food ahead!
The pedometer in my heart
《私の心の万歩計では
１万を超え ２万を超えて…》
says we passed 10,000 steps... 20,000...
《２万150歩あたりから もう…
数えるのは やめた》
Once we hit 21,150 steps,
I stopped counting.
The scenery
《景色が ちょっと
変わり始めていた》
was starting to change.
The stones out in the fields
are worn down by their daily existence and disappear
That's their trial
When will we be able to resist fate?
Before you lose all hope
and say that we can't win against gravity
go without stopping
past the goal line
You have such strong convictions
Leave your footprints on this Earth
Maybe their tiny length will cause a miracle in the end
Give us a magnificent jump
Run now and do it
Jump past all you see overhead
This is your stride
＜もう おなか すき過ぎて
目がかすんできた＞
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#49 Nitta the Leader
Man, I'm so hungry, I feel faint.
＜早く 食料 見つけなきゃ
私の嗅覚で！＞
I'll use my nose to find us food!
＜おい 新田！
たまには 後ろ見ろよ｡➡
Hey, Nitta!
Look behind you once in a while!
A leader shouldn't ditch his followers!
リーダーが
仲間 置いてって どうすんだ？＞
What? You're already tired?
＜何だ？もうへばったのか！➡
宇宙飛行士になったって
すぐ宇宙に行けるとは限らない｡➡
Being an astronaut doesn't mean you immediately get to go into space.
If they're ranking us, we have to finish on top!
順位がつけられると
分かってるものなら➡
全部トップを狙わなきゃ
ダメだ！＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Nitta the Leader"
Nitta!
＜新田～！＞
(新田)＜あ？＞
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
The first Japanese ISS commander is training hard!
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
カッコいい！
Cool stuff!